class number four it's called the
investigation of the chapter five
elements yeah good we are investigating
the elements the five elements this time
which includes no space good why this
okay for spending too much money
let's make it a twenty dollar question
why do you think he chose space raise
your hand if you want money I mean if
you don't want money just a Buddhist
fight ten dollars each okay if it's
correct I think it's because it is
harder to understand how does to
understand most difficult okay yeah
that's about three dollars because if we
can understand the emptiness of space
then we will be able to understand the
emptiness of the space then we will
realize that the space is unchanging
isn't it twelve dollars you want to add
anything you guys can do it together to
understand the definition of space and
by that we can understand that space is
empty as well oh you guys are too like
1995 it's one more thing I want one more
thing if we understand the emptiness of
space within he understands the
emptiness of other elements that's okay
that's okay okay anyway I will give some
money to myself two dollars okay
ten ten shopping
okay space is an object which is defined
by the absence of something you think
space is an object which is normally
defined by the absence of something you
see so space has its own gotcha
okay what's the Guardian for space
what's missing in space physical stuff
yeah physical stuff now have we talked
about physical stuff recently last
chapter okay it's a flow it's a flow if
you can see the flow in the gardener's
wisdom you're a very cool person okay
because otherwise it just seems like
he's just different subjects for no
reason you know it doesn't seem like the
chapters connected to the chapters okay
if you can understand the flow of the
chapters then you really started to
understand the guardian okay so there's
a flow to this connection to the last
chapter last chapter we talked about
your physical body and all those
molecules and atoms okay and now we're
moving on to space because the
definition of space is the absence of
concrete stuff okay okay right and it's
often used to describe emptiness okay
now space is empty of something which
really exists which is physical stuff
like this unbelievably cool meditation
sign okay after we become a famous
resort they will charge you $200 for
this thing but probably you can get one
now for five dollars 500 or 5 let's say
10 I think it's very Sejong bong you
should get one for your house teach your
husband what it means okay it would take
some explanation but you put it on your
door when you're meditating okay
and you hope somebody notices it alright
anyway
now the the space where this is in okay
this is in space right this is occupying
space that space is still empty okay see
if the space wasn't emptied this will
get pushed down
this'll get pushed down so there is
empty space and this we're gonna call
this thing meditation time some tow home
tom tow is occupying that space okay and
that space doesn't have physical form in
it or else this would be pushed out you
think so it's empty it has a gotcha that
gotcha exists it really exists okay
but space is what gives things a place
to be okay
some people try to define space as the
distance between the microphone and
Geshe Michaels list okay some people say
this is space this is the element of
space from here to here okay that's
their definition of space that's not
Buddhist space okay Buddhist space means
where's where's the thing sitting empty
chair and the thing sits there and then
the thing leaves but the chair stays
right empty chair stays got it okay so
it's very similar to emptiness okay so
space is a very popular topic in
Buddhism because there's a gotcha
there's something which is not there and
allows other things to be there okay got
it
so of course the gardener is moving on
to space because it's the most difficult
element but it's also the most similar
to emptiness it's very similar to
emptiness there's a gotcha
there's something missing okay got it
that's probably why he went on to space
okay
and a lot of meditations are called
space-like
okay meaning you think about the
emptiness of things okay
or you can space out okay and I like to
say those of you who studied the for
space meditation which is very very
helpful we won't have time to do it this
week it's too much going on it's in the
DC IDE level I don't know seven you can
do four kinds of space very helpful very
helpful idea
okay what's the gotcha in the kitchen
yeah you need anything husband the I
didn't do anything husband okay
is he there no he's not there he's
impossible does it feel like he's there
yeah that's called ignorance okay first
link of first thing so Gong can teach
you the wheel of life expert I hope you
will teach in Bali the wheel of life it
would be nice okay it's going deeper and
deeper his book is going different
different they make a good Wheel of Life
team together okay
hmm okay good so I am the gardener in
this chapter v chapter he's trying to
prepare our mind for the idea of gotcha
okay something missing okay something
which is define by something missing
okay got it where is the human computer
oh I got a judge whether you can get
this okay hundred bucks but it has to be
perfect because you have to be perfect
definition of space traditional
definitions today's exact words there's
four by the way if he doesn't do for I
don't have to pay right okay if he does
five if that's three if he does the
wrong for I want the definition of space
from Scripture five four three two one
do be okay say totally captain Tory got
some it's definition in space talk rank
means her stuff you can touch ok stuff
you can touch sanghas name means talk me
his called cannot touch do you know why
his ass Sangha means not know talk and
they say because his wisdom cuts through
things like a hot knife through butter
okay so a sanga's name means okay like a
very sharp knife didn't just cut through
the things okay his name is no talk
topless topless okay now in the
definition of space talk reg means
anything you can block you okay physical
thing okay God Tom means simple absence
simple absence just not there cannot
cannot stop in it cannot stop it's open
it's free you can move into it okay
that's a definition of space Sato rate
carton
reg means touch it talk means to hit hit
touch stop
just hit touched up just hit just
touched up just it's the definition of
space hit stop
sorry he touch stop just it's the
definition of space okay that's I've
been looking for a name from my band I
think it's it's gonna be pretty good
what I say hit touch stop hit touch stop
just I'm sure it's gonna be popular
maybe not okay all right
first I don't have a band because the
guy had a baby I hope you guys are doing
well Aaron okay now then I he gets in
soto Craig got some right is a easel is
a phrase right it has words touch sorry
hit touch stop just here touch stop just
okay that's the traditional definition
of space okay that's the traditional
definition by the way I like to say
empty space sometimes I like to say
empty space because it doesn't mean
outer space it doesn't mean the place
where you fly long march Rockets to the
other side of the Moon okay it's not
done it means there's space right here
okay so sometimes I like to call it
empty space okay the definition is that
okay and we we started to talk about it
yesterday
but Buddhism is very deep about the
definition of definition
okay the definition of definition
because in in Buddhism and especially in
the gardener
we are very precise about our
definitions okay if you're precise about
your definitions you'll have less fight
with your husband okay if everything's
clear okay totally clear how do you
define a trip to teach in the other
country in Romania how do you define
that how many days exactly who's
watching the kids you know who's gonna
pay for it this is called the definition
of a trip to Romania okay so your life
is easier if you define things clearly
in your marriage and in your life okay
so Buddhism is Buddhism is very big
about definitions okay there's a
definition of a definition okay I got it
I went got it for you okay from Adams
text let me go get it so we're going to
talk
the definition of a definition okay the
definition of a definition says a you
chew some tongue Ziya to some tongue say
it means substantial something you know
physical real something substantial okay
like table like how many days exactly in
Romania and how much money
exactly it's gonna cost us you know
exactly we want exactly say here means
substantial J means stuff J is related
to the words R which means clay or
ceramics in okay so it means as real as
this substantial the word for
substantial means clay or porcelain okay
the person in the second link of the
Wheel of Life is a guy he's a Potter
he's even called zackin which means a
mr. Azad or hak-kan means a doer so our
business person says odds aim is real
substantial okay Chism sama means what
mr. human dictionary I mean come on for
free okay just some tongue yeah three
qualities have to be there for something
to be a definition three qualities have
to be there for something to be a
definition and those must be substantial
okay here we go
what are the three I don't remember
cheer tinium beset your sanema
that thing is a definition okay so
generally speaking the three qualities
the three requirements of a definition
first I mean it has to sound like a
definition okay just in general
somebody has to say this is the
definition it's a definition it's a
definition okay
probably it should have a few words in
it that described that thing right so
sound it should sound like a definition
okay the definition of
lunches anything getting Michael likes
okay all right
secondly Frankie said she tended cement
tuba with a correct perception a person
can see that it applies to what you are
defining if hot and burning is the
definition of fire then the second
requirement to be a good definition is
that fire should have hot and burning
okay so the pieces you use in the
definition must apply to the thing you
are defining okay so listen it's hot and
burning a good definition of fire yeah
it's hot and burning and always frozen a
good definition of fire
no because the third thing doesn't fit
the thing okay that's all so first of
all it should sound like a definition
should have parts you know certain
qualities okay that sounds like a
definition right the definition of fire
is hot burning and always frozen does it
sound like a definition it sounds like a
definition so choose any Emma it's the
first quality is there but it's the
second quality there no because always
frozen doesn't apply to fire okay so so
far two of the three qualities of the
definition the definition of a
definition okay the definition of a
definition number one it should be a
list of qualities okay now you ready hot
burning and always frozen is it a list
of qualities yes it sounds like a
definition number two do all of the
three qualities I just talked about
apply to fire now okay so Senshi means
the thing you're defining also called
Sencha okay the thing you're defending
andum in logic but you can just say the
thing you are defining what are we
defining in
chapter 5 mainly space mainly okay all
right now okay
what's the third part of the definition
Ronny Keats and John Lee churching it's
any me chepa it shouldn't fit as the
definition of anything else
it shouldn't fit as the definition of
anything else the definition of a Toyota
is any vehicle with four wheels okay
the definition of a Toyota is any
vehicle with four wheels good definition
no cuz if it's other stuff
it fits Fords and Chevrolet's and Subaru
isn't okay got it
so the definition should be that guys
definition on other people's definition
it should be specific to that fire okay
got it
cool now Justin Thomas those three
requirements of a definition it should
be a definition the part should fit the
thing and the definition shouldn't fit
other stuff like Fords and Chevrolet's
and okay those three requirements those
are easy any anybody can agree to those
but the first part of the definition was
as a you say you made substantial so
something about a definition must be
substantial okay what it's easier to
understand what substantial means if we
try to understand what's not substantial
okay
what's not substantial
Veronica always makes me enchiladas when
she comes unless hustle makes his I'm
not hinting okay I'm just saying I had a
great Chilean on last night from certain
person from God that was amazing
I was in chile relleno heaven for like
an hour
so she'll you know she'll say well you
know make you some enchiladas when I get
there and I'm like yeah please come to
die Mountain for your spiritual
advancement
she'll be here Friday you'll see her on
Friday I think but then sometimes she'd
get busy her mother's not well right now
so she maybe she has to stop and finish
she cannot come okay then that enchilada
just became name only name only okay
that enchilada is not gonna fill up my
stomach okay it's a name only few my own
but my camera kitchen word $35 I don't
know why mom Obamacare children mom but
my camera to chant Mamba good it's 25
okay I had to help him
okay shopping 25 the only purpose I
teach at the amount is to Easter it's so
word can make money from me
yeah MOBA McEachin means it's a cool
idea in Buddhism a future thing which
will never happen a future thing which
will never happen my enchilada
Veronica's mom isn't well ok she will
stop and finish I will never get the
engine ok that enchilada is called takia
state a cure name only name on me ok is
it called enchilada yes can you eat it
no it's not Zia it's not substantial got
it when she comes here she has time she
makes him nice enchilada I eat it
that's daya that's substantial she talks
about enchilada her mom gets more sick
she has to stop and finish she never
gets here then it's a name only
enchilada ok and it's not gonna fill
your stomach why are we talking about
name only the definition of the thing
you're defining is name only enchilada
which will never happen
Ganon you should be confused are you
confused I hope you're confused ok the
definition of something to give a
definition is it's not real it's not
substantial it's just the idea it's just
a picture
ok it's a picture of an enchilada you
try to eat a picture of enchilada
you're gonna finally lose your stomach
understand it doesn't have any calories
got it so somehow fire has to be named
only and the definition of fire is real
is substantial ok Zia
okay then you have to understand that
about Buddhist definition okay now in
the West in America we talked about it
the other day definitions are kind of
like sentences okay
the definition of a lousy boyfriend is
he never puts his arm around you and
when you want a hug okay that's the
definition of a lousy boyfriend and it
seems like a sentence it seems like a
sentence and sentences seem like words
but in Buddhism it's the opposite in
Buddhism it's the opposite okay the real
thing is the hot touch and to burn your
finger that's the real thing the
definition is real then what's that
definition of fire Agni sharp-edged our
feijoada about showing open
a Guan ball straight ajar okay a big
fire is called pure in in Russian okay
so that's just the word it didn't hurt
you right when I said pooja did you go
no it's too hot in here already
I didn't the thing you're defining in
Buddhism it's just a word okay
ty you're to samsara tired to some
tongue okay and the definition is
substantial hot burns your finger okay
usually we think of definition as a
sentence and we think the definition is
just words but in Buddhism it's the
opposite okay which means you ready in
Buddhism the definition is the real hot
and burning and it's called luck Sharna
selection or luck you know so that's
your 20 years Sanskrit words
for this Homer is lucky onna Lak sh ama
lak sh a na okay luck Sheena it comes
from well LexA or latina has two
meanings okay Lakeisha or election er
has two meanings one is definition okay
one is a sign or an indication a sign or
an indication okay how do you know your
husband's upset you get a lecture on his
face red color okay got it
the red color is a lucky know that he's
upset okay
it's a sign it's like a road sign
husband upset red color okay that's
called lacunae okay so it's interesting
that the word for the sign on your
husband's face that he's upset red color
is that that is the word for definition
in Buddhism sign and definition are the
same word in Buddhism sign and
definition are the same word in Buddhism
anything that has these two signs is hot
and it burns your finger that's fire
that's fire in fact the the name for
definition in Buddhism is science okay
signs of fire hot and burns your finger
okay got it
if that now listen if someone comes up
to you and says you said Pajar in the
class you said pajara it took you like
half an hour to remember the word from
your college russian but you remembered
pajara you said Pajar
not pajamas your anyway you said Pajar
in the class can you please tell me what
is pajama okay now at that moment you
think pajamas is the thing because these
Russian people are all yeah pajama
that's right
so it must be a thing okay but at that
moment what does it look like in your
mind if you don't know Russian it's like
a blob to me it looks like jello I don't
know why undefined
all my fly came to you maybe your games
are more interesting okay now think
about it think about it when you're
learning a new word right somebody says
Pajar and you're like oh all those
Russian people in the room are going
like that so it must be something it
must be a thing in Russian it must be a
thing what's your picture in your mind
of that thing to me it's like jello it's
like piece of jello it's going like this
it's clear it's a thing but I don't know
why it's just a thing right it's kind of
for me before you define something but I
know it's already a thing I don't know
it looks like yeah all I can say is
jell-o jell-o is a dessert my mom used
to give it to me because it's cheap okay
we had four boys no no father but it's
like this it's like a jellyfish you know
it's like so before you tell me what is
Pajar you say oh guess not you have a
poisson can i pick up a pitcher at your
house I'm like I know you're talking
about something but I don't know why you
talk about yeah okay God in then what
happens - lock comes nonsense sashing
super hot and burning they then the
suddenly the Pajar got more real you
know oh yeah fire okay fire like on the
stove or in a cigarette
now the mental picture changed right
before it was a clear piece of jell-o
and then I said hot and burning and then
suddenly all the mental picture became a
you know a fire somewhere some fire in
your life but usually your stove or
something okay so the thing to be
defined by John was it substantial or
was it just kind of just a name yeah
before I gave you the characteristics
before I gave you the substantial
characteristics okay therefore the thing
which you're defining it's just a blob
right and then I start giving you
characteristics substantial it will burn
your finger if you touch it and as you
get your hand closer it starts to feel
warmer and warmer
oh and then suddenly the mental picture
becomes a fire okay so now here's the
gardener's question what time I supposed
to finish the clothes 10:30 9:30 10:30
okay I guarantee you a pee-pee in the
next five minutes okay what was I
talking about
oh here's the big deal about Chapter
five already which came first the fire
or the definition which came above that
wasn't my question
the guard you know talking to the other
guy which came first
beautiful but you're too early beautiful
answer but too early don't tell the joke
until I'm ready what who says the The
Blob came first The Blob came first
right Raj our little blob
then came the definition right then you
put the definition on the thing if
there's no blob there's no place for the
definition to go all right right no it
needs a place to go a definition must
arrest on a theme right hot and burning
must rest on there has to be a pissant
there there has to be a blob there right
the blob has to come first right cannot
yeah you're right because it cannot be
hot and burning and tell it to until the
definition comes until the hot and
burning comes it's not a fire right how
do you know a fire needs to be hot
burning oh I saw a fire before Oh in
that case the thing you're defining came
first right and then you decided I will
make a definition of this thing huh
burning why because you have observed a
fire you can't make a definition unless
a fire is there already and it cannot be
a fire until it has a definition
until it's hot and burning it cannot be
a fire right see it can be hot so before
it's hot it can be a fire yeah but how
can you how can you have a fire until
you have hot and burning how can you
have a definition of fire and tell you
how hot burning first and then you give
the definition to things which came
first the fire or the hot and burning
that's all I'm asking tell me you kept
PP which came first
now tell us come on yeah either one is
wrong come on we are studying the
gardener he always tricks you
which one came first hot money and the
de fire cave or there was a fire and we
decided the definition of fire should be
heart burning okay
which came first okay me again okay I
lied about the toilet okay I'm sorry
just a few more minutes me Ken McKim is
called there are four factors in
Buddhism okay four kinds of basic causes
DCI level seven five causes four factors
well I'll teach it to you someday this
is called Mikan okay McCann means the
object which triggers a perception the
object which triggers a perception okay
look at the cup in my hand right now
wait
keep looking then it triggered I held it
up first and then it triggered a
perception in your eyeball your eyeball
this rods and cones
some of them change white so then she
kept red then you saw the thing it
triggered the perception in your mind
what chapter
it was a long time ago chapter 3 chapter
3 you know which came first the eye or
the car no McKim the cup triggered the
eye person the cup changed the cells in
the eye right the cup came first right
yeah both choices are wrong okay this
isn't a gardeners style this isn't the
gardener style he wants you to go like
that something weird here I don't get it
he said fire and come first hot and
burning comfort the I was there in my
head then Galya pick up the cup or did
the cup wake up the I was the I already
there well what's happening what's going
on okay if you're not confused
you don't understand the gardener okay
if you're not confused you don't
understand the gardener the guys didn't
want you to be confused why where did
fire come from where did the blue come
from where did I come from the cop and
the eyeball came from one comic see the
cup and the eyeball
came from someplace else don't ask me
did the I come from the cup or did the
cup come from the eye bad question bad
question they both came from karmic
state therefore make coffee for other
people
okay don't forget that therefore the
gardener lodging is not the garden and
logic is not just to prove emptiness the
garden is logic is to help other people
Gani if you don't reach if your logic
doesn't read reach helping other people
you're not studying emptiness you didn't
get it okay
the final logic is therefore you must
serve coffee to other people therefore
you must share your coffee with other
people
therefore if there's people in the world
who don't have food
you must share your food therefore
therefore okay
there's always a new gardener therefore
you must feed other people you cannot
ignore people in Africa you cannot
okay because that's where the cups
coming from it wasn't the eyeball first
or the compass first or the fire was
first or the burning was first it's that
other people need you that's where the
logic has to go otherwise you're not
otherwise it's not emptiness got it
you are not some physicist pushing the
switch and I hope the world doesn't blow
up let's check that's in the garden okay
take a break PP yeah hi okay just a few
more minutes I think 15 more minutes
okay here we go
so what the other guy is doing right who
is the other guy in these three chapters
he's an accountant good and he's like
this boring I'll be down in nerd he
keeps bringing up basic basic basic
basic basic Buddhist teachings right
first chapter I'll be done with kosher
it's called the Chisum the three topics
which are boom come KJ so say poo come
can't you soon
yeah we're talking about the parts of a
person we're talking about the eighteen
parts of and we're talking about the
sense organs mainly okay these are the
very famous topics of the first chopped
oh I'll be Dharma this is the Nerds
Bible okay they're big okay
and in general we know that the other
guy said to Nagarjuna
look these are teachings by Buddha these
are the first thing Buddha ever said
they must exist from their own side they
are real
don't tell me they're not real it's the
first thing Buddha ever talked about but
it's not gonna sit down and talk about
something that's not there I mean that's
crazy okay especially the first talk
okay these guys are going to Vancouver
right you guys are going to Vancouver
and the CSP gentle gentle gentle
those ginger CSP people now they become
real gentle they're going to Vancouver
to to talk about their success stories
okay then you know the first thing you
stay in Vancouver
you should look smart dress nice you
know then if you want to lie lie the
second time or lie the third time but
don't lie the first time okay you have
to make a good impression
you have first bunch of Big Buddha first
teaching he just became Buddha he waited
49 days before he talks then probably he
was combing his hair and buying his food
and I gasps and the very first thing he
said come on that's gonna be the best
thing he has okay because he want
everyone to see how smart he is same as
Vancouver the first thing you say you
have to say something great right in a
new city
right so the accountant in Chapter three
four five
he says blood this is the first thing
Buddha said when he got up on the stage
in Vancouver and now that the the the
ninth trip the tenth trip maybe he run
out of good things to say maybe he say
something crazy but not the first trip
he will say something good he wants the
people to come back don't don't say he's
safe Fosters and I'll tell you another
thing each of the topics he talked about
has a connection which is natural
doesn't come from me does not come from
me okay
each of those three topics chapter three
chapter four and Chapter five they are
talking about a connection which is
natural nobody made it up okay
it's not a creation of my mind my seeds
okay it's just nature that's the way
things are okay what was Chapter three
the eye sees stuff nobody made it that
way that you can't have it when you look
at this ugly green drink there's a
connection between the eye and the green
nobody made it Naggar tuna come on the
ice job is to look at colors
that's all that's what the that's what
the ideas colors are what the eye sees
and the eyes job is to see colors nobody
made it it's just that's the way things
are you can't have eyes without green
well you can have orange that's all come
on that's just natural nobody gets a lot
didn't wake up this morning saying oh I
better make a connection between my my
coffee Brown in my eye you know it's
just natural okay
second when the next chapter chapter 4
what come on go to the atoms go to the
atoms yeah every molecule has some
element element stuff and every molecule
has touchable here both smell things
that come out of it
nobody come on there guys you know
nobody made that just like didn't get up
in the morning and say I better get my
atoms working you know I got to get my
fire atom working so I can have some hot
coffee
okay nobody made those things
no those connections are unnatural
what's the third one chapter five worse
and worse luck Shana lucky Anna but
what's the old meaning of machina sign
sign look new gardener when you get up
to have coffee in the morning you don't
have to glue the heart on to the fire
you don't have to go to the to the
hotbox in the burn box and take out
something and then start the stove and
put the heart and put the burn on the
fire the fire has it always it's natural
got it
you don't wake up and turn on the gas
and then look look around for the hotbox
get some hot find the burn box then put
it on the gas Dennis fire no come on
it's automatic
okay got it its lucky Anna okay cuz luck
Chandler has two meanings right number
one definition that people make for fire
but there's a more intimate lacuna that
hot belongs to fire it's always
connected to fire the root for the word
luck you know that you're gonna put on
your homework is laag lug lug okay and
it means connected to glued to okay
blood means glued to got in alright
there's our one it's done hmm
there's a word Claire Claire button
write in Russian Russian Tsar is closer
it's glued on okay right
it's that glue yeah come from the same
root look okay so by the way if you want
a cognate because you have to do your
homework
you can say leech okay leech leech is a
special worm that lives in the old hot
water and when you step in the water the
leech will connect connected so the word
leech means connector who likes to
connect himself to your skin and then
it's difficult to get them off it's
difficult to take them like a polar mom
okay so the word leech means connect
connector animal okay who connects to
you okay what's the point what are we
talking about here lucky nut can mean
definition but it can also mean sign
it's hot and burning gala they're glued
to fire all the time okay
they're glued to fire blood means glued
to okay they're always glued to fire
Legion comes from that if you're
interested a group of people glued
together to fight for the Roman Empire
okay the same route okay so look nobody
woke up in the morning and put the lock
Sheena on fire to put the science on the
fire is it's always like that it's
always like that okay so the word lacuna
is supposed to make you feel
self-existent natural natural okay
nobody made it you know forever fire has
been hard nobody put hot on fire okay
who said that you have to say it with
the correct accent nobody put your heart
on the fire and the fire it's all look
okay nobody okay that's the other guy we
always the structure of Nagarjuna it's
an investigation right
who who we investigating in this chapter
yeah the accountant the lug guy the
Luxan the guy watching our definition
sign automatic nobody made the fire hug
okay got in okay the definition of an
aspirin
okay ready is that it takes away your
head that's ask anybody ask anybody in
the world
what's an aspirin oh you know you take
it your headache goes away that's all
taking away your headache is election of
aspirin okay it's a definition and it's
part of it it's it's what makes the
aspirin aspirin lecture makes the
aspirin aspirin got in okay in the
gardener chapter three you had problems
with orange color and the eyeball you
know you said that connections no
automatic okay they're kind of far away
maybe you're right maybe you're right
okay then we went to physical body you
know the chemicals in your body didn't
create your skin well you're getting
closer
I mean you eat it yo chow you get fat I
mean there's some connection okay but if
you don't like that one
how about next chapter let's talk about
really tight connections like fire and
hot who could divide fire from hot you
know who could say hot is not part of
fire who could say hot is not part of
fire got in so he's talking about
natural connections natural connections
got it doesn't ask is an aspirin
connected to taking away your headache
I'll say it again
now listen it's important is an aspirin
connected to taking away your heaven
headache
no have to ask when your take don't work
come on do you didn't notice and the God
is like it didn't bug you it didn't
bother you when your mom said do you
remember that moment I remember where I
was I remember exactly I was in my
brother's room cuz I was throwing up and
my mom said here take aspirin then I'm
like two hours later I'm like mom it
didn't work she says that's okay
sometimes they don't work I'm like I
should have asked her what's the
definition of aspirin but I'm like okay
you know mom is God right mom is the gun
I'm like okay mom okay Aspen's don't
work sometimes right but fixing your
headache is the lecture okay
it should have done that connection is
natural okay what's a sign that the
luxury of aspirin is not natural
sometimes sometimes you have aspirin
which doesn't have that like you know
yeah but Gila it's a definition of an
aspirin yeah but sometimes it doesn't
have it do you doesn't it feel weird to
you don't you think it's coming from
somewhere else maybe you have to do
something else to make the aspirin work
maybe you should help other people who's
talking in the gardener he's like you
didn't notice that the aspirants don't
work sometimes where have you been the
last 20 50 years okay oh it's the sign
of an aspirin it takes away your
headache yeah but sometimes it's not a
luxury
lecture notes are not connected to their
objects automatically naturally okay
who connects them your good deeds
the gardener always goes back to good
deeds okay I'm gonna stop there we're
out of time but you know there's kind of
fun we had time the last thing Tony lama
ever does
in each chapter he goes to the sutra
which supports it and if we had time
that would be a really like dessert
every chapter we could have like yo
tower Trudeau
some people say I'm hinting for Trudeau
in the class now then somebody said just
like don't hint about churros in the
class
someone's gonna miss the class and go to
Wilcox and buy churros I'm not asking
the class is more important okay but
between classes just kidding so in each
chapter
Tony Lama ends the chapter by quoting a
sutra by showing you the sutra okay so
I'll put it in the translation I'm
hoping to chance like this immediately
so I don't forget everything okay so in
my free time I will try to I'll try to
give you a translation within a few
months okay
there's a big problem with the Sanskrit
the Sanskrit is available but it's
corrupt in there because it was
handwritten so there's a very great help
from Beijing there's a very good scholar
who worked very hard to find the
Sanskrit so that's been very helpful
what's his name's Danny sure sure sure
he's good I don't know who yes but he's
good you should think of him and I'm
using his book his sounds good it's
pretty good okay all right okay we only
have about 15 minutes so I'd like to
check if it's possible to confuse
someone about the gardener in only 10
minutes okay so that's my goal this
morning we only have 15 minutes so my
special goal is it possible to confuse
somebody with the gardener in only 10
minutes
okay let's try okay ready okay here we
go
did you put on your seatbelt okay
all right we're almost finished with the
investigation of the elements and we
chose space first okay and a very cool
thing happens at the end of the chapter
and if you don't if you're not mixed nut
what's it mix nuttin if you're not one
of our translators okay in our special
translator team or pure gold then you
don't know about this thing but at the
end of the chapter the gardener says I
don't care which space you're talking
about they're both wrong okay at the end
of the chapter he says I don't care what
space you're talking about they're both
wrong okay dinner
if you don't know Buddhist philosophy
you you won't understand what he's
talking about what he's talking about is
the different idea of the element of
space in the abhidharma school and in
the second school the sutra school okay
the two law schools lo lo lo is
sustained Li but Stanley Bundy's text
I'll be Dharma first school lo lo school
means better than any of us okay right
we know that
so first course they have a certain
definition of space and the second
school has a slightly different
explanation of space both of them don't
understand emptiness in the way the high
school what's a high school middle way
okay so we have to talk about what's the
difference between these two kinds of
space all right then we can finish the
chapter and we can get more confused
with the next chapter
okay by the way the next chapter is
called
desire and attachment an investigation
of desire and attachment but we have to
finish the element chapter okay so
there's two kinds of space in in
Buddhism first one I'll be Dharma now
listen
space does something like fire like
water like wind like Earth like carbon
like oxygen okay like gravity it does
something okay it has a job
it does something anybody want to guess
for $20 okay Tim wait before you answer
just so I'm trying to help you make
money what function does space what the
space do Lois school it holds its a
place it's the place where objects exist
in yeah you can say that occupied you
can say that water makes things flow
fire burns things and space is like the
guy at the restaurant the maitre d right
the main waiter at the restaurant who
says I made a place for you look you
know I have a recipe here's three these
these three chairs are for you guys
space does that here's the orange juice
I need a place to stay where can I sit
did spaces okay hey look I made a chair
for you over here okay and then it goes
there okay so space is like the guy in
the restaurant who gets the chair gets
the other customer out after they give
the tip kick them out
and then it says I have an empty chair
for you so you can it's just for you you
can come here you can be here okay so
I'll be Thomas cool since space has a
function space does something and it
makes sense because the other four
elements are famous for causing
everything physical okay we talked about
it in Chapter three okay the elements in
your body the four elements have a job
to create your eye to create your ear to
create your nose to create your body
okay
got it so it makes sense if there's a
club with four people in it who all do
something then if there's a fifth member
joins it he has to do something unless
it's the AC I'm sorry Diamond Mountain
board of directors just kidding if a new
person joined the team they have to do
something right they have to do
something okay got it
so that's who said that I'll be Dumber
good the next cool suture school said no
no yeah space has a job but it's
negative its negative okay it just
doesn't stop people from going there
it doesn't stop people it doesn't do
anything okay you know you go to a
nightclub there's a bouncer you know
bouncer big mean guy if the people get
drunk in a nightclub he will kick them
out right how I know about that I just
found the movies okay and somebody you
know have to kick somebody out out of
the chair you seeing I mean that's not a
function they just don't make it
available okay they don't help you they
just don't do anything to help you get a
chair okay so they say space doesn't do
anything space is not smart
space doesn't think to do anything space
is just an absence of anything okay
space is just an absence of anything
okay let's take this book which you're
gonna buy I mean let's take this book
okay
so it's a physical object okay and space
this job is just not to block it okay
so space doesn't do anything second
school second school space doesn't do
anything space just absence of physical
thing
this is space space is just the absence
of physical date space didn't do
anything you put the book in the space
you take the book out of the space the
space just there okay absence of
physical thing okay got it
hundred dollars now I've seen
neuroscience come human dictionaries
trying to be cool he's like
this is a difficult one
how doesn't the gardener now the first
place okay we talked about it right I'll
be dumb space does something right we
beat it already and I'll I'll give that
one to you for free with definitions and
what is getting the definition the
timing of the definition which came
first the space to be defined or the
definition we finished that okay that's
how we beat the abbiamo guys for $100
how do we beat the second group guys and
then we can go to the next chapter
how do we beat the second group guys
$100 no it's our existing thing wait you
only get one gasps human computer yeah
it is a situation but that's not the
answer if there's something physical in
the space the space is still there not
not the real answer yeah what's the
question how do we beat the second
abhidharma
how do we beat the Salonika idea of
space their idea of space I will repeat
space is the absence of a physical thing
okay how do we beat them and it's
difficult it's very similar to the
argument about the eye and the object of
the eye it's very similar if the absence
of the book comes later the space is
very sophisticated and Rome
okay I'm gonna tell you wait and it's
very simple because then I have to tell
you the book I'm drinking you look at
the bird
look at the bird focus on the way okay
if the book doesn't come from its own
son if the book doesn't come from its
own side then the absence of the book
cannot come from its own side because if
it does they can't have a relationship
we talked about that already we already
talked about that but you forgot okay
we're at the end of chapter five what
was chapter five about yeah
the elements right we were talking about
space right then at the end of the
chapter you can guess what he's gonna
say what it can you guess for $0 yeah
give the money to a few what's the last
thing he's gonna say come on next to the
last thing but it's a good guess
somebody was listening in class
yesterday thank you yeah exactly
Allisyn shopping zero dollars he's
perfect okay yeah it's the same for the
other elements okay
now something interesting that part in
Tony Lamas commentary is missing okay
someone made a mistake when they carved
it so we have to find other copies all
right who started doing that word I
guess okay word talk to Ben Kramer okay
where's human yeah there's a problem
there's a there's a big problem with the
carving something's missing in the car
there's missing those that part okay you
find it we found part of it in Russia we
found part of in Beijing we found part
of it in East China West China so but
we're missing is still missing some
pieces okay so we have to find it all
right we have to try to find it okay
more copies more copies
JB Mongolia find one in Mongolia and
french fries okay
yeah it's very interesting that it's
missing something's missing
couple lines are missing now in that
commentary and you're gonna learn as you
become a translator if you become a
translator and somebody later put in a
garden of verses into his commentary
Tony Lamas come to me okay
and they made mistakes okay they made
some mistakes and it's kind of
irritating okay that's another it's like
this they put in some they put it in the
wrong lines okay and a little bit
different translation they used a
different translation so in ancient
times like in schwinn songs times five
people tried to do the translation and
then one became popular okay
usually the best one became popular but
not always
okay it's just like English translations
so somebody put the gardener's poem into
the commentary in the right place but
they they used a different translation
and that's the one of the translations
that did not survive
okay so the one translation was carved
500 years ago 600 years ago and the rest
of them died they disappeared because
the carved one became very popular
but sometimes the Karma is not the best
one and we have different ones or
sometimes one piece of the card one is
good and one piece of the old one is
good so that's the case here so it's a
lot of extra work for G Michael okay and
I have to compare the Sanskrit there are
five or six sense good versions and then
I have to check the guy who put put it
into the commentary and we know it was
somebody later because it doesn't fit
you can tell Tony Lamas using a
different translation okay so these are
problems for me for my life okay
you don't care alright anyway
you just want okay yeah
then she make my life more miserable
okay yeah so there's a part missing
there's what all those studies correct
there's a little part missing about
first he talked about how there are four
elements right cannot cause your
physical body and your eye your ear your
nose and then he talked about space
which in the second school is a
unchanging thing on producing absence of
something absence of something I had a
many moments in my classes with my
teacher so you know 30 years I'm sitting
with another guy
his Tibetans a little bit better than
mine and his Sanskrit is a thousand
times better than my I hate him you know
I still hate him I
I try not to talk about it but he kept
giving the best answers in class I hate
it and then one day he interrupts a
llama I'm like yeah see he interrupts
the llama and he said I just thought of
something
and remember taste one and he said all
unchanging things are negatives absences
all unchanging things are the absence of
something and repete goes you know what
you're right and they're not super
jealous still super jobs but I try to I
try to look nice okay
if you get a chance to study with him
sometime his name is art and go I hate
to say his name even okay but he he
doesn't teach much but he he's a good
teacher in New York if you're in New
York area okay all right so anyway we
covered
we covered the emptiness of changing
things okay like fire water earth okay
in those molecules red and the molecules
are making up physical stuff and that's
definitely a changing thing because my
hair is falling out got it
changing wrinkles are coming you know
but in Arizona we get these spots then
so that's changing and in space
according to the second school is just
the absence of something so that's
unchanging okay
it doesn't change Y hundred dollar
question nope okay okay I'll say it
again space
in the second school is defined as the
absence of physical stuff now why is it
true it can never change Janice if
you're wrong retaining me 95 ok it's
worth the risk
just kidding it's because it's emptiness
doesn't change
it's either 100% empty or it's not empty
it yeah good you're on the right track
I'll give you 75 ok ok
if it changed a little if if the absence
of change a little bit then a little bit
of stop the clock will show up Boop
got it mmm is there an elephant in this
room is that changing or unchanging yeah
if it changed then elephants nose will
appear here you see 1% change I'll say
it again
is there elephant in this room can that
is it changing or unchanging can it vary
like this can I get more or less no
because if it changed 1% you'll have 1%
of elephant appear in the room it's
impossible
right so absences are always 100%
absences then you of course the
seven-year-old monk in the monastery Oh
Jerusalem it's austere yes sir
I have a question what what elephant
stick his nose in the room but his
buddy's out of the room did it not
emptiness anymore like yeah yeah okay
I'm not talking about that okay got it
emptiness that elephant in this room is
unchanging why if it changes 1% the
elephant's nose will appear here because
1% of the elephant will appear here ok
got it
you okay yeah it's a $75 answer to $100
okay
then the guy and this is part of the
missing page in the carving' okay it
should be there maybe fun to write it if
we can't find it
the missing page should say the guy the
other guy says what about things that
are in between what about things that
are in between okay changing things and
unchanging things and then imaginary
things okay which are not really things
okay can you imagine pink elephant in
the room it is it changing or unchanging
the pink elephant the pink elephant
right so it's jut doesn't have more
existence than not thinking about does
the pink elephant in your mind have more
existence than the pink elephant had
five minutes ago then you're thinking
about pink elephant tell you one thing
about pink elephant so there must be
some difference or are you thinking
about pink elephants all the time you're
nothing about people what are you
talking about of course there's a pink
element
it's just imagine we call imaginary okay
it's not real if you can't say changing
or unchanging so the guy tries to come
in okay you ready
before we move on to chapter six okay
and we leave the accountants behind okay
before we move on to chapter six got it
then one more guy comes and he says okay
you're chapter three chapter four if
you're talking about elements
I understand changing thing now chapter
five you talk about space unchanging
thing but I think there's a real nature
to imaginary things okay okay hmm that's
a way
the the idea in your mind is an
unchanging thought yeah I start changing
thought you can say that but I'm talking
about the elephant not the thought about
the elephant okay imaginary okay can he
carry teeth trees or something no okay
all right okay and then he he they argue
about that
there's no commentary that's missing
okay you'll have to wait
somebody had to write it
okay now last thing at the end of many
chapters the Guardian insults the other
people okay not really cuz he's Buddhist
he doesn't really insult them but he
makes a kind of a just before he says
goodbye in the chapter he will he will
say something like so here's his/her
okay a stepfamily to push aunty nasty
from chopped papaya Bhavan on Danish
anteater stub your passion
Shivam and he says this the badness
laudanum
yep Anita many do tawa de natal a
Chinese your scimitar no June okay I
gave you the Sanskrit on your homework
everybody's like why say ALPA Budi Budi
Alba means tiny tiny little tiny like
Kili like curry Sangeeta chunky poco
poco chicky-chicky changi tow Chiquito
okay I'm gonna forget that one okay so
alpha means small alpha means small in
sanskrit but we're more interested the
one you have to know is booty say buddy
okay you know Buddha means butt right
the root food means to understand okay
Budh root means to understand so Buddha
means the person who understands
everything knows everything okay and the
word that the gardener used here is
alpha booty so but he not Buddha okay
good he means mind your mind okay
there are many words in Sanskrit for
mind um one is booty okay then he says
you guys who are alpha body mini
intellect mini intellect mini brain okay
he calls a mini brains
hey mini brain it's kind of funny in
sentence you can learn all these special
insults from the ancient books hey ALPA
building a mini brain mini brain what
makes you any mini brain astitva to
patient in a state bomb you think things
exist you think things have to exist or
don't exist
you think you mini brains Alper booty
guys you think things have to exist or
not if you don't know how to stay in the
middle okay you think everything should
exist or else it cannot exist and you
cannot find the middle way and you're a
mini brain driving a minivan you are
crashing every
you are unhappy you have an unhappy life
you are crashing okay got it
mini brain okay alright okay cool what
does it mean for $100 I keep trying to
give away $100
you can't answer twice in the same
morning okay new rule okay word just
whispered to her and she can okay now I
want to know if somebody says come on
get low if something doesn't exist
the only other choice is if something is
not existing
the only other choice is that it's not
existing okay
what does it mean you crashed your
minivan minivan mini brain minivan into
existing or not existing and you lost a
middle way okay a fierce collecting
money
maybe he's gonna donate it I'm gonna try
so if you say things that are existing
and you crash into the existing thing
thinking that means you are thinking
which things exist by themselves on the
outside $50 and if we say you crashing
to the other side you say they don't
exist at all we don't have any existence
120 wait wait take it to the kitchen go
for 140 take it to the kitchen
that kitchen will be the husband you see
the husband is yelling but he's yelling
because you see him yelling and he
doesn't anyway which is the existent
which is teutonic okay gotta run bottom
run exist would be like the husband is
there is yelling by itself I didn't do
nothing
good good you gotta say it with passion
and that exists will be
I'm imagining the husband's there and
and no one yelling at me
yeah be become become there's no husband
become there's no husband okay
does it help no ok hundred and twenty he
gave 120 ante when I say hundred forty
hundred and forty good answer so if you
are Alba booty
Minnie Minnie brain mini brain person
you think things have to exist or not
exist he is closing the fifth chapter
okay
he is closing the fifth chapter with his
middle finger I miss something like that
okay excuse me but that's my nature
okay now the last line of the fifth
chapter is very cute Tao attained eat a
chihuahua never she were she meetin
anybody who looks at things that way
we'll never see nirvana okay anyone who
looks at things that way will never see
okay he's playing he's playing all the
way back to the third chapter because in
the third chapter we discussed looking
with your eye right so he's kind of
closing his accountant section three
chapters his last word to the accountant
sister you know hey Minnie brain don't
think the husband in the kitchen exists
the way you thought and don't say oh he
doesn't exist
there's no husband in the kitchen don't
don't make those two mistakes keep to
the middle way okay
then he says if you keep looking at the
husband the way you look at the husband
oh he's angry cause he had a bad day he
hungry he had a long time with you if
you keep blaming this wrong reasons
right
then you will never if you keep looking
that way you will never see nirvana
okay guys what is the definition of
Nirvana for I don't know we got some
money honey I'll just give away a little
more okay but still have enough to get
home 30 bucks
[Music]
nice okay Sam and was it how do you pump
a sauce or tango yeah she gets thirty
dollars by the way shopping okay Austria
welcome Austria nice to see you okay you
Austrians have to come to the program in
Berlin because I can't do two in Vienna
and Berlin cause it's too much for me
because I had to go to a sort of BIOS
you can blame this again okay but I
figure you're so close to each other so
I cheated the Austrians I told them to
go to Germany
okay I understand so fight with them
don't find me okay all right if you keep
looking at things that way you will
never see Nirvana
okay that's his final thing but they're
looking is a joke because the third
chapter the beginning of the fight with
the accountants was talking about
looking and now he's closing up the
accounting chapters three four and five
okay
and then he says you will never see
nirvana and the definition of Nirvana is
if you understand that the accountants
are wrong you can stop your negative
emotions forever okay if you understand
the accountants are wrong you can stop
your negative emotions forever
okay and if you keep looking at things
if you keep in the kitchen if you keep
thinking the husband's coming from the
husband you will never see Nirvana okay
you will never see Nirvana and Nirvana's
definition is you lose your desire you
lose your hatred right you lose your
desire you lose your hatred guess what's
the next chapter last let's investigate
desire okay
is that a cool way to bridge segue to
the next chapter got it
so at the end of chapter 5 is like okay
you accountants I'm done with you if but
I just tell you one more thing if you
keep looking in the kitchen at your
husband the way you've been looking at
your husband in the kitchen then you
will never see nirvana
then he goes to the next chapter what's
the next chapter investigate desire
investigate desire okay